Hi, welcome to everyone's favorite
segment, mailbag. The honor of the first
opening today goes to fellow video
blogger, Fran. Good day, Fran. Don't
even have to say her last name, everyone
knows Fran. Well, if you don't,
subscribe to Fran's channel because
she's awesome. Fellow video blogger,
co-host of the Dinosaur Den with Bill
Hurd,
owner and designer of all the Fran Tone
audio gear, and
space aficionado, and the list goes on.
She's got an awesome YouTube channel. If
you're not subscribed to it, you should.
Do yourself a favor. Now, let's see what
Fran has sent. It's going to be
something
interesting, no doubt. So, thank you
very much, Fran. She's in Philly, by the
way. Hey, if people don't know If people
are overseas and they don't know Philly
in the US, of course.
So, let's crack this open.
Here we go.
What has she sent? I'm surprised at the
amount of money
it cost to ship something like this.
What does it weigh?
Does it tell you the weight on there? I
don't know. Like, it's a kilo or
something. Like, over a kilo. Probably
jumps up. Surprised at the cost. The
United States Postal Service,
quite expensive. So, thank you, Fran,
for sending this in and to everyone who
sends stuff in cuz it does actually cost
a fair bit. So, let's have a look. Hang
on, should I smell it cuz it's probably
vintage. Fran is really into vintage
stuff. And is she going to have another
hand-typed
type, you know, with a
proper typewriter?
No characteristic smell. Let's have a
look.
What What have we got here? What have we
got here?
Ah,
it's a That, I believe, is the Liberty
Bell, is it not?
I've I've seen National Treasure, one of
my favorite movies, of course. Yes, I
know how corny it is, but I do like it.
Um I believe yes, Parson Stowe, that is
the Liberty Bell, the cracked Liberty
Bell.
Remove before use.
Oh, okay.
A genuine Liberty Bell, which is in
Philly, is it not? Or it was in Philly
or something, I'm not entirely sure.
Sorry. Um
let's have a look. Yes.
There is a note.
There is a note. Oh, postcard. There we
go. Is that Liberty
Greetings from Philly, a Carpenter's
Hall Independence National Historical
Site. Here we go.
Let's have a look.
There we go.
And yes, there is a hand type letter. Um
I'm sorry, Fran, I forget what
typewriter you used, but it's pretty
schmick, apparently. And let's see what
she has sent in here.
Uh let's
All right, here we go.
We've got ourselves
some vintage
Let's have a look. OOH. OH, WOW, LOOK AT
THAT.
Chinon
Genesis 2
old school camera. Wow, let's check this
puppy out. Never had one of these. That
is going to be a retro tear down
Tuesday. Oh, fantastic. Nice.
Nice nice ergonomics on that. Don't mind
that at all. Not too shabby. Wow, old
school. And no,
none of this digital rubbish. Thank you
very much. Let's have a squeeze through
the viewfinder.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Oh,
very nice.
And Fran doesn't disappoint. Look at
this typewriter. Now, if I was more of a
typewriter aficionado, I'd be able to
tell the particular type used here. I'm
I Is it like an IBM golf ball? One I
don't know.
She's going to scream at me. Sorry,
Fran. I don't know.
Anyway, we have a gadget here. Yes, it
is a high-resolution camera from the
1980s. The real-time low-latency monitor
is amazing. We'll check out this
low-latency monitor. And it operates
entirely with just available light. It's
incredible. Doesn't need any power at
all. It took decades for cameras to
reach this level of resolution that
these uh 20th century cameras could
achieve. And I'm sure that I'll enjoy
the wonders that hold within. I'm sure
we all will. Let's do a two two-minute
teardown after we check it out. Thanks,
Fran. She's from the United States of
America.
And playback is not instantaneous.
Bloody 20th century cameras. I don't
know.
Next up, one from Dave Lee. He's good on
you, Dave. He's from the old dart and uh
I don't think I need this.
Just
paper packaging, can't we?
Hey.
And
it's wrapped.
It's a present.
Woohoo! I should let Sagan open it.
A pair of shoes! What I've always
wanted! Yay! No, I doubt it. Okay,
what's in here?
Duh duh duh Duct tape. Beauty.
Sealing it with duct tape. Let's have a
look.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah. Watch this.
Hope I can get as many views as that fat
kid with the lightsaber on YouTube. How
many did he get? How many hundreds of
millions? I don't know.
Uh
No, it's young Anakin's.
No. No. Come on, bring on the new movie.
Original trilogy only. No, this
This did not happen. No. Merry
Christmas. Love your biggest fan. Thank
you very much, Dave. Um I guess he
figured I wouldn't open it until
Christmas. And yeah, based on my form,
that's a pretty uh reasonable
assumption.
Look what we've got. We haven't had one
yet. Tada!
Sinclair ZX Spectrum. Yeah, baby.
Woah, it's a real keyboard.
Caution, do not poke or jab people or
animals with light saber.
And Dave sent in this Sinclair ZX
Spectrum Plus. And we've had the ZX
Spectrum a couple of times on the blog
before uh doing teardowns of that, but
this is the Plus model. Essentially, the
same as the previous version except it
has some upgraded RAM. I believe even
the board's interchangeable. And the
keyboard is of course different, but
Uh
it looks good, but then you go to use it
and this is quite simply the most
horrible feeling keyboard I've ever
used, I think. Not so much in terms of
the action of the actual key, but the
shape of the key. What idiot came up
with this? This is one of those classic
seemed like a good idea at the time
ideas where they would actually curve
the top of the key in like this. Oh,
that'll help with the ergonomics of you
know, your key won't accidentally slide
off and hit the one next to it. Yeah,
maybe in principle, but in practice it
is horrible.
I like how could any like, you know,
fair enough coming up with the idea of
it and then having a go at it producing
it, but then you'd go along and use it
and surely you would go that feels like
Like no, let's just not bother,
but no, somebody signed off on that.
Made in the Republic of Korea by
Samsung. There you go. Who would have
thought designed
by Sinclair in the UK though, in
Cambridge, sorry. And that's it. We're
in like Flynn. This is 1984 issue by the
way, even though it's got copyright 1983
on there. This one came out in '94, I
believe. Anyway, look, they've still got
the that dodgy bracket on the regulator
on the linear regulator over here. Just
got like afterthought. Geez, terrible
mural for a plus model. And there's the
Ferranti ULA or uncommitted logic array,
essentially a PLD and a programmable
logic device. And you can see the date
there, 48th week '84. So, this one was
manufactured basically essentially sold
essentially early 1995 '85, sorry. Geez,
back to the future. And there's the Z80
CPU for all you aficionados. I know
there's a lot out there and
interestingly, this one is like early
'84, 8th week '84. I'm surprised they
had stock sitting around for that long
because the Z80 CPU back then was like
red hot stuff. I would have expected it
to go straight into
a production product somewhere. So,
yeah, for it to hang around that long,
almost a year before it actually makes
it into a product, that's rather
surprising. And there you go, some of
the RAM. Actually, this dates it even
further is into
the first quarter 85. So there you go
seventh week fifth week 85 STC. Don't
they make like baked beans as well? And
the keyboard while it might have those
fancy pants keys on it it's just
basically the same membrane as what was
used in the previous one. It's just got
better key tops that's all. They're
still conductive rubber backed onto the
membrane so yeah spongy feel. So thanks
David for sending that one in. I think
we've had our fill of ZX Spectrum stuff
for now mailbag. What do you think? Next
up one from Martin Clements. That rings
a bell. Is he having a second suck of
the sav? I don't know. He's from
Livingston in
yes Livingston in the United States of
America. Let's check this puppy out and
see what he's sent in. We love a big
package.
Nothing better than having a big
Let's go.
Excellent.
Recycled material.
Can always use that for packing so I'm
always packing and sending stuff. What
have we got here?
I've got a postcard presumably from
Thanks very much for your excellent
show. I've been a fan since 2012. Thank
you very much. You've got a lot to catch
up on.
I was recently cleaning out his airplane
hangar as you do. I was cleaning mine
out just the other day you know. And he
came across these old
things. Let's check them out.
Wow. It's a 300 A
Navomatic.
Yeah it's the Navomatic. Excellent
that'll make a good two minute tear down
and
oh Apollo
GPS. Check it out. Aircraft GPS system.
That would be uh
pretty state of the art in uh, relative
terms, I guess. And Martin's from
Montana, there we go. Nice-looking
Montana, I want to go there. Look at
that. And he sent in these from his own
personal hangar. Well, thank you very
much. What we've got here is an old
analog autopilot, the 300A Navomatic.
Yeah, you can rely on that puppy. Oh,
brilliant. So, we'll check that out.
That's, I don't know the age of that,
but jeez, that's got to be That's got
like '70s or something written all over
it. Um,
and then we have a, uh, a Morrow, uh,
Apollo 1. This is a, uh, Loran receiver,
so we'll take a look at that. And then
we've got a GPS receiver down here. It's
the, uh, once again, it's a Morrow, uh,
brand Apollo. And ejector button.
Ejector button. Hello.
Oh, ejector button. There. I just pulled
it out. Check it out. It's got, uh,
Garmin uh, flybry?
Flybry, as in library, but it's flybry.
Get it? Data card.
There you go. So, this must have, I
presume, uh, GPS, uh, waypoints and
things like that for, you know, cuz
there's no mapping capability on here,
right? So, it's not like, you know, it's
going to draw, you know, maps and give
you routes and things like that, right?
But, um, it would have, I presume, uh,
even though I know nothing about
aviation, would have the, uh, GPS
waypoints for, like, all airports and
things like that, so you can like call
up the nearest airport and, you know,
all I'm talking like small airports and,
uh, things like that. So, there you go,
it's actually fairly recent, uh, 2012.
They still make these things because,
you know, you I presume to get a GPS,
uh, qualified for aircraft use, even if
you do have to qualify, and then, you
know, a
lots of planes are still going to be
using these old units. So, they probably
still maintain stuff like that this even
today, even though it's, you know, these
things are absolutely ancient, they
still they probably cost a pretty penny
as well. Return expired data cards. Here
you go. Yeah, I don't think we'll return
that, but there you go. It's a It's a
library data card for a presumably a
Garmin GPS or did Garmin just actually
make the data cards and the waypoints
and things like that? And this is
generally a uh Morrow or whatever. Let's
I don't know. 2-minute teardown on each
one. And here's inside our old-school
308 Navomatic.
Look at that. It looks like potential Is
that that board there looks uh
conformally coded. But anyway, whole
bunch of vertical riser boards which
contain most of the circuitry. There's a
little bit on the bottom down there. And
as you can see the bottom side,
old-school just hand-taped artwork. No
date code yet, but check out all the
adjustments on here. Woah, HDG gain,
null, whatever that is. No idea. Anyone
know how these analog uh um autopilots
work? I've got no clue. It looks like
we've got some sealing though around
there, is it? So these little
uh these trimmer
pots are sealed. So I know. Actually,
no, they're they're just screws. I
thought they might have been
uh trimmer pots, but they're not.
They're just
screws holding in these data cards. Aw,
let's take them out. And wow, I totally
called it. Look, 1970s.
Wow, look at this.
70 17th week '76.
Wow, for a 1458
op amp.
Unbelievable.
And every autopilot must have a triple
five timer from 1974
for the win. Wow. Hold on to your hat.
We can beat that. Look at this triple
five timer here. Look, 51st week 1973.
Thank you very much. And a 741 op amp
from 1973.
Brilliant. 4016 from '74.
This is great stuff. And check this one
out. I reckon someone's had a go at this
4016 because if you have a look on the
back, the soldering
is different
to the others. Look.
Look, it's just it's not It's looks like
it's been hand redone. Doesn't look like
it's the You can see the flux residue.
Doesn't look like it's original wave
soldering. So, yep, it's been repaired.
And our final card in there is a summing
amp. There you go. Look, they label each
board. Lovely.
Look, there it is. Summing amp. So, that
is a really nice plug-in design. They
just plug in, go into these vertical
pin headers here, and then they've got
these plastic strips on the side to, you
know, board separators to space them
apart. That is That's a That's a lovely
design, you know? It's nice and
mechanically robustic. I can understand
why, you know, this sort of
construction's done in that planes. And
that's going to last a long time. Bet
your bottom dollar. I'll tell you what,
I'm keeping these boards because these
have got, you know, really classic dated
early triple five timer and 741 and
other chips on them. Absolutely
brilliant. I'm going to
definitely don't toss those out. They're
They're a piece of history. Now, let's
take a look at this Loran or LORAN
receiver. I'm not sure how you pronounce
it. I'm not in the industry, but yeah,
this is a basically a pre-GPS
navigational aid. It would pick up the
transmissions from
Loran transmitters like, you know,
spread throughout the country around the
world and from that measuring the uh
time differences you can uh calculate
your position but it's basically been uh
completely superseded by GPS but
probably you know old aircraft uh still
have it. They probably have it as a
backup. Um I'm not sure if they're
maintaining the Loran transmitters and
things like that but yeah if the GPS
system you know goes down for some
reason I don't know war starts or
something and they shut it off then uh
we can you know you can still navigate
using this. I'm not sure what the uh
accuracy of a something like this is uh
you know of the system is but it you
know it'll get you to the nearest
airport within visual range of the uh
nearest airport definitely and uh you
can land. So yep let's take a look. I
have no idea how any of this works at
all but there you go bearing and range
and all sorts of stuff. Made in the
United States of America. Woah look at
this all digital that's a digital side
anyway driving of course there's going
to be an analog uh board down the bottom
for the receiver but that's uh driving
the display and doing probably doing the
you know the timing and calculations and
everything else and we'll take a look at
the processors. A keeper that's got a uh
oh that's a rechargeable no is it? I
don't know but no a lithium battery in
there that it that could be cactus we're
talking 1983
here look at that and the chips are
dated uh
uh mid 83 as well so yeah but it's in
it's in good nick look at that that's a
nice design nice and reliable I like
that classic 8085 for all you fanboys
out there and of course the 82 uh 55
down there. There's our EPROMs uh we've
got some memory it's all happening. Wow
look at the analog section isn't that
beautiful nicely laid out nice and
modular lots of look I mean you know
here we've got some big inductors here
and caps so what are these? Are these
like uh band pass filters and things
like that? I'm not sure of the
frequencies and everything, you know,
all sorts of whatever it is, but jeez,
there's lots of them. Look at that. So,
a ton of stuff and it's all uh
Look at this. It's all like sequential.
So, there's like multi-stage
stuff happening everywhere. Some 3080
op-amps and
What's under here? Actually, if you have
a
close look down in here, my guess of
what's happening here, right? We've got,
you know, selectable filters and then
we've got some transistors down in here,
here and here. So, obviously, these
transistors, well, I believe, are uh
used to switch in various um LC filters
here. So, that'd be my guess of what's
going on. Maybe similar thing happening
here as well. Oh, that's a bit
uneventful. I thought it would be some
sort of, you know, a whiz-bang, you
know, frequency ionized oscillator or
something like that. I don't know. It's
just the switching power supply. Oh, and
some of the transistors in here, MPF's
uh 6521.
That's just a um
uh amplifier, so nothing uh fancy. We've
got a 2N6727.
That's just a uh high power uh switcher,
basically. And well, that's about it.
So, yeah, I don't see anything in the
way of uh RF transistors. So,
I reckon they're doing some switching,
switching the filters in and out. So,
that's a solid bit of uh aircraft
engineering from, you know, the early to
mid '80s. Very nice, and it'd still work
today. It'd be ultra reliable. And yeah,
no worries whatsoever. That's just
brilliant. And now, this Apollo GPS
unit. Be interesting to see the data
this thing, whether or not it was, you
know, post uh 2000 when Clinton turned
off the uh selective availability and
basically gave, you know, super precise
GPS navigation to everyone and started
the geolocation movement and everything
else. So, that's when it really boomed
and took off. If it's pre that, but you
know, you still even with selective
availability, you still had like a 100 m
or 200 m, you know, accuracy or
something like that. So, um you know,
that once again would have been good
system perhaps in terms of accuracy.
Once again, it'd get you, you know, near
enough to the airport
and then you can land the damn thing cuz
you can see the runway. So,
you know, it would have been good
enough, but let's take a squeeze. And
bingo, there it is. Once again, very
neat, very tidy, very professional, and
no surprises for finding a separate
receiver in here. They would have just
used, you know, a receiver from the
experts in the business. In this case,
it's JRC. Is that Japan Radio Corp who
make the transistors and various things?
I'm not sure unless there's another JRC
that do that. We can have a look at
Hitachi H8 chipset, but this jeez, this
would have been real old school
receiving. None of this 12-channel
parallel rubbish. No siree, Bob. And
from the date codes in here, we're
talking '93, '94. So, there you go. At
'94, maybe made in '95 or something like
that at the latest. After a small
search, I couldn't find any info on that
main chipset there at all. So, I'm not
not sure what's going on there. Big ass
socketed ROM, of course, and there's the
Hitachi H8 with lithium backup on there.
901.
Is that 901? Is that to be replaced?
Expires at 901 or was it replaced 901? I
assume it was replaced. And there's
inside our can. We've got some Murata
oscillator, and Murata oscillator up
there, 14.4 mega up there. Don't know
who the manufacturer the
NDK, sorry. And oh, look at that puppy.
Love those packages. That's an RF if
there are RF I see. RF amp, probably RF
preamp if there ever was one. So, yeah,
like power in out. That's basically what
those things are. And on the back of
that board, we've got some good old
62256, are they? Yep, 62256 SRAMs. Geez,
that brings back some memories. Used
plenty of those back in the day. And
yeah, nothing special, just awesome
passive stuff on the bottom. Although
this was under another metal can by the
way, which went in these slots here. And
that's rather interesting.
Got that trace there. Does that go off
to there or is that just flapping around
in the breeze? It's the fly buddy GPS.
Awesome name. Copyright not in '94. And
we've got state-of-the-art 80C186.
Thank you very much. PLCC package. Love
it. Oops, we need to put a resistor in
series with our with our backup battery.
What the So, that's pretty much all I
expected in there. We've got some
digital processing to get this serial it
would be a serial output coming from
this old school GPS module. I'd love to
get some data on this. I don't
don't think it's like a 12 channel
thing. Oh, that could be. I don't know
if they had that back in 1994
is it or not, but yeah, anyway, yeah,
it's would not be nearly as sensitive or
nearly as multi-channel or you know,
nearly as advanced as today's modern GPS
receivers. Not even close.
Um
Like it's not even using like a big
thing back when you know, 2000 hit and
selective availability, you know, the
surf chipset was one of the major ones.
You know, it's it's looks like it's
whatever this thing's doing some sort of
digital processing and Hitachi H8.
That's it. There's no you know, this
thing might be a custom
ASIC perhaps, but I you know, I don't
know what's going on there, but yeah,
nothing like the advanced Surf chipsets
like they had in the years following.
So, thank you very much Martin for
sending in this gear. That's been an
awesome set of teardowns. This video is
mailbag video has turned into a teardown
video. You know, a teardown bonanza. So,
it's fantastic. Thank you very much
Martin. That's an interesting look some
aircraft stuff that aircraft
flight instruments that we haven't seen
on the blog before. Awesome. Next up one
from Australia. Good on you Matt. He's
from Geraldton in WA, Western Australia
that is for those who don't know.
Been to Geraldton. Nice place.
And let's have
squeeze what he said. It's heavy.
Weighs a fair bit.
Got a note. Don't want to read the note.
It's a spoiler.
So,
there we go.
Yeah.
All right, bit of crap.
Tiger's bag.
There you go. It's a lappy.
Is it? I assume it's a lappy.
Little uh 12-in job, is it?
No.
Yeah, hang on. No. Oh.
Oh.
What is
Oh. Oh.
Oh, there's hang on.
There's all this black
Something has disintegrated. Absolutely
disintegrated.
I don't know
what the hell
happened there, but
oh, it's all has it all come off the
It's all come off the curly cord. Yeah,
all right, yep, yep, it's fallen apart,
the curly cord
to this
phone. Is it one of these
satellite phone things? What the Yes.
Yes, it is. Old-school satellite phone.
Oh, no.
It's not the greatest design, is it?
And check out this puppy Matthew sent
in. It's a look, an old-school satellite
phone, Thrane & Thrane. Sounds like a
bunch of lawyers. Anyway, made in
Denmark. Hi to all my Danish viewers,
terrific.
So, what we clearly have here is the
receiver, like a pop-up antenna. I like
this. Microwave radiation, beware. What
the hell? Is it Like is it actually a
mic Is this actually I don't know.
Actually may not be a satellite. It
might be a directed microwave link, a
microwave phone or something like that.
Anyway, clearly the antenna up here,
we've got ourselves a little RF patch
cord, which goes down to here. So, this
would be the receiver and or, you know,
what the transceiver down here, and then
just the phone with the cord, which went
all crusty, all the plastic on that just
went completely cactus. So, 2-minute
teardown. Might take more than 2
minutes, but hey. Wow, check out inside
the antenna. It's got some sort of
spongy
Yep, it's got spongy type
material in here, and
ta-da. Now, I guessed it looks I'm just
some copper sheets embedded
in the front there.
What the Look at this secret RF voodoo.
Here we go. Look at this. Anyone know?
Anyone want to hazard a guess exactly
how that works? Any uh
microwave RF
antenna experts in the house? We've
obviously got our antenna point here,
and then it's branching off controlled
impedance lines. This would be a
specific dielectric backing here, bet
your bottom dollar. And then basically
it splits off. We've got four patch
antennas, and once again we've got
various other like you know these are
different impedances for I don't some
sort of you know impedance matching.
It's not like we're doing any you know
real filtering there or anything like
that. But anyway, we've got ourselves
four separate patch antennas like that.
Very interesting. Why? What advantage
does that give?
But wait, hold on to your hat. It gets
more interesting. Flip that out and
tada! I expected just to see a coax
going from here to here. But no, look.
We've got ourselves a transceiver in
there. And
these are interesting.
Huh. Look.
Do not eat.
Okay. So what are they? Some sort of
desiccant modules or something perhaps?
And there we go. There's under the can
there. Yes, we've got some RF stuff
happening here. Big RF power transistor
there by the looks of it. Oh yeah. Yeah,
we've got some filtering, got some uh
probably some band pass filtering
happening in here. There's our coaxial
antenna output. I really like that how
that just you know matches up to that.
That's really jazzy. Um and once again
we've got another
got some more filtering happening in
there. And look. Ah. None of this PCB
rubbish. Look, we've got ourselves some
nice little hand tweaked inductors in
there. Check them out. Well, I'll tell
you what these lawyers at Thrain and
Thrain really know how to do some
engineering. We've got some nice solid
diecast casing in here. Oh yeah. man.
Look at this.
Ah, it's a thing of beauty. Look at
that. So, obviously what we've got here
some battery pack which
Matthew had to remove, unfortunately.
Then up there once again, this is our
obviously our DC to DC converter. Comes
in here, generates all of our voltages,
goes over all sorts of digital stuff.
We've got an Analog Devices DSP down
here. And it looks like we've got some
sort of programming
you know, SIM card thing which goes in
here. Then we've got the lower level
transceivers in here as well. And then
just yeah, digital processing and a
speaker. And not much else to it. Serial
out, whatever. And then the phone
outlet as well for the handset. And
Bob's your uncle. And there's nothing
fancy pantsy happening under those
shielded cans there. Nicely delineated
into the separate modules there. Very
neat. I mean, this is you know, even
with the budge up there. This is you
know, this is real professional design.
They really know what they're doing.
There you go. Two Analog Devices DSPs.
No surprises for finding something like
that in there doing all the audio
processing and stuff like that. Looks
like we have ourselves a power amplifier
using the diecast alloy case down here.
That's nice and the cutout in the board,
screwed down. And it has some heatsink
compound on the back of that. It'll have
a big thermal pad, big single inline
package. Well, turns out this puppy down
here from ST the L3 thousand in I'll
link in the data sheet. It's a SLIC,
whatever that stands for. Anyway, it's a
line interface
basically ringer circuit design
interface to the telephone lines. A
pretty advanced
little beast. It's really
very purpose specific device. So, thank
you very much Matthew. That's an
interesting beast. If I can actually get
some info on it exactly like satellite
phone microwave phone, transceiver
thingamabob, shoe phone, whatever it is.
Um,
try and link it in or if you've got like
a manual for this thing or something
like that, please let us know. Thanks,
Matthew. So, I hope you enjoyed today's
mailbag. Thanks for everyone who sent
stuff in. It wasn't many, but it turned
into a teardown bonanza. Awesome. If you
liked it, please give it a big thumbs
up. Discuss it down below. All that sort
of stuff. Support me on Patreon. Buy my
t-shirts. You know, all that sort of
stuff us YouTubers have to say to
survive. Catch you next time.